Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project, 593058
  - Fields, [Unknown], Undated; 592018
    This interview was conducted at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. The interviewer and date are unknown, as is the first name of the narrator. The main topics of the interview include Mr. Fields' life in Austria-Hungary; his immigration to, first impressions of, and early experiences in the United States (US); his employment; his leisure activities; and his living situation in the US. Fields recalls his early life in Vienna, Austria-Hungary, including his father's employment with the Hamburg America Line; his memories of the 1918 flu epidemic; his employment by two of the major banks in Austria; and the effects of the 1929 stock market crash on his work in Vienna. He discusses his immigration to the US, including his loneliness and seasickness during the voyage, and his belief that he would have died in the Nazi concentration camps had he not left Austria-Hungary. Fields' first impressions of the US include feeling comfortable in New York, New York because he had seen it in movies; realizing that his immigrant status would prevent him from finding employment commensurate with his experience; and prioritizing finding a job and a place to live.
    Fields discusses his employment, including working for an antique fabric dealer; teaching German and French through the Works Progress Administration; censoring the letters of German prisoners of war for the US War Department; and working in a factory. Fields discusses leisure activities in which he participated, including hiking, rock climbing, and cycling; reading On the Origin of Species by Charles Darwin; watching Charlie Chaplin's propaganda films and his belief that Chaplin was one of the greatest comedians of all time; and enjoying music and the theater. He discusses his living situation at the time of the interview; feeling that he never found a decent place to live; being convinced that his landlords were mentally ill; and believing that if he wrote a book about his experiences living in furnished rooms he would make a lot of money.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens IV.
  - Fischetti, Maria, 1974 May 8; 593215 (Box 90, Reel 874a, Box 1, Folder 24)
    Maria Fischetti was born in 1901 in Sant'Angelo de Lombardi, Italy. She married in 1916. Her husband immigrated to the United States (US) about a year after their marriage and she immigrated to the US in 1920. They lived in the South Brooklyn area of Brooklyn, New York and had six children. She worked in the garment industry and was a member of an unspecified union (likely the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America).
    This interview was conducted by Joan Granucci at the Congress of Italian Americans Organization (CIAO) in Brooklyn, New York on May 8, 1974. The interview covers Maria Fischetti's early life in Italy, her immigration to the United States (US), her working life, and her family. Fischetti discusses her early life in Sant'Angelo de Lombardi, Italy, including her family's vineyard and her courtship and marriage. She discusses her husband's immigration to the US; his work as a peddler and construction worker in the US; and her life with his parents before her immigration in 1920. She discusses joining the workforce after her children were grown and working in garment factories making sweaters, ladies' coats, and men's suits. She discusses her husband's illness after she returned to work and his willingness to do housework while she was at work. Other topics include her religion; her children; differences in South Brooklyn over the 50 years she lived there; and her volunteer work at CIAO.
    See also: Family, and Neighborhood.
    Index is available for this interview. An electronic transcript of this interview is also available by request.
  - Fox, Abe, 1973 July 3; 593217 (Box 90, Reel 876a, Box 91, Reel 876b - 876d, Box 1, Folder 25)
    Abe Fox was born in Russia in 1890. He was one of eight children, with four brothers and three sisters. His father made and sold glass windows. Fox attended school in Russia for two years before apprenticing to a tailor. He immigrated to the United States in 1906 and lived on the East Side of Manhattan, New York before moving to the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1916. He married when he was around 20 years old and had three children. He worked as a tailor in various shops in New York City and was an active member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 23.
    This interview was conducted by Mark Hirsch on July 3, 1973 at Abe Fox's home. Fox's accent, his tendency to mumble, and the fluctuation of volume over the course of the interview make him hard to understand. The interview covers Fox's childhood in Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1906; and his work in the garment industry in New York, New York. Fox begins the interview by describing his childhood in Russia, focusing on anti-Semitism in his hometown, which included pogroms and abuse by the police. He recounts not being paid during the three years of his tailoring apprenticeship and receiving meager pay for his long hours of work after his apprenticeship. He recounts the Socialist Revolutionary Party meeting at his house and learning more about Socialism at the library until his library card was destroyed when it was learned that he was Jewish.
    Fox explains that he immigrated to the US in 1906 after several failed attempts to illegally cross the border into Austria in order to sail from a port in Poland. He discusses living with his aunt's family on the East Side of Manhattan, recalling his acclimation to the spring weather and the low cost of food in New York City. He describes his first job in a garment shop in New York City and explains that, in the beginning, he had to bring his own machine to work. He notes that although he joined the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) Local 23 in order to fight for better wages, hours, and working conditions, change was slow due to factions within the union and corruption among the union leaders. He recalls a strike that occurred in the early 1950s, through which workers acquired a twenty percent wage increase despite conflicts with strikebreakers brought in from Chicago, Illinois. He discusses the ILGWU opening a school to train machine operators and the union becoming more inclusive, particularly in terms of the Italian population's involvement. He explains that different skill levels and job types had different wage standards in the union and discusses working conditions in the garment shops. He recounts that he established a ready-made garment store on Pitkin Avenue in Brooklyn with his brother and step-father, noting that the people paid to guard the store broke in and stole all the merchandise.
    Other topics include a comparison of his impression of the US before and after his immigration; his tumultuous relationships with his father and step-father; his lack of knowledge regarding pregnancy and sex prior to his marriage; his leisure activities, including reading the newspaper, playing pinochle, and attending shows at the Jewish theater; and his views on the birth control movement, the rise of political power among the Cuban and black populations, and the migration of Jews to the suburbs.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration; Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast; and Passage.
    Antisemitism |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.; Pogroms |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.
  - Fox, Gladys, 1975; 344068 (Box 16, Reel 59a, Box 17, Reel 59b - 59c)
    Gladys Fox was born on the island of Nevis in Saint Kitts and Nevis. She worked as a teacher until she immigrated to the United States in 1947. After her immigration, Fox worked in a dry cleaners and as a pediatric nurses' aide before studying early childhood development at Fordham University in the Bronx, New York. She worked at Morrisania Hospital in the Bronx until she retired in 1972 and was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    The interview with Gladys Fox was conducted by Jay Facciolo at the offices of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York in 1975. The main subjects of this interview include Fox's life and career in the British West Indies, her immigration to the United States (US), and her work in the US healthcare system after her immigration. Fox discusses her life in Saint Kitts and Nevis, including being the youngest of seven children; her father working as a carpenter and being away from the family because of his work; and learning to read, write, and perform multiplication and division by the age of four. She recalls beginning the process of becoming a teacher in the British West Indies at 15 years old, and becoming frustrated with her lack of advancement after teaching for over 20 years. She mentions her immigration; the fact that she initially came to the US with no intention of staying permanently; and the fact that she was required to leave the country through Canada before she could become a citizen. She recounts living with her two older sisters in the US, and feeling that she was imposing because she was over 40 years old when she immigrated. She discusses having trouble finding well paying work; receiving a certificate to be a pediatric nurses' aide; and studying early childhood education at Fordham University in the Bronx. She discusses working for hospitals such as the Flowers Fifth Avenue Hospital in Valhalla, New York; St. Luke's Hospital in Manhattan, New York; and Morrisania Hospital in the Bronx, New York.
    Fox elaborates on her time at Morrisania Hospital, including the fact that she was quickly given a supervisory position. Fox recalls that there were disagreements between the staff at Morrisania Hospital and workers contracted from Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx, because of differences in pay; and becoming a member of the Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union. She also mentions that she still worked for the Local 1199 at the time of the interview as a corresponding secretary, sending birthday cards to retirees; attending conferences; and serving on a number of committees.
  - Frasca, Corrado, Undated; 344069 (Box 101, Cd ref60, Box 17, Reel 60a - 60b)
    Corrado Frasca was born in Pollago, Italy on February 6, 1908. His father died when he was six months old and his mother remarried. He had two sisters and one step-brother, all of whom remained in Italy. Frasca married and had one son. He spent most of his life as a longshoreman but also worked as peddler, grocer, and brewer of moonshine.
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz and Frank Farragaso at a senior citizen center on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York (likely the Carroll Park Senior Center). The date of the interview is unknown. This interview covers Corrado Frasca's childhood in Pollago Italy; his illegal immigration to the United States (US) in 1926; and his life and work as a longshoreman in Brooklyn. Frasca begins this interview by describing his childhood in Pollago, Italy, recalling doing simple jobs for the local fishermen and seamen when he was eight years old. He explains that he moved to Genoa when he was twelve and worked for several years aboard a passenger ship. He discusses an uncle in New York encouraging him to come to the United States, and Frasca jumping ship in Norfolk, Virginia in 1926. He describes traveling to Baltimore, Maryland to avoid the authorities and locals who spoke Italian coming to his aid by giving him room and board free of charge. Frasca explains that his uncle brought him to Brooklyn where he began working as a longshoreman. He describes shifting occupations depending on the seasons; working on ships going to South America in the winter; working as a longshoreman in Brooklyn during the rest of the year; and later establishing his own business as a peddler and fruit seller. Frasca mentions joining a club established by immigrants from his hometown and the club providing social and fiscal support to its members during hard times. He describes how he met his wife, an American citizen, through his uncle, who served as a matchmaker in their apartment building.
    Throughout the interview, Frasca describes a tension between his Italian heritage and his new life in the US, including his refusal to be stationed in Italy during World War II for fear of fighting his family and the way in which he gradually learned English through his wife and conversations he had with non-Italian longshoremen with whom he worked. He describes the differences between his generation and his son's generation, noting his opinion that the younger generation is less social and less attached to traditional family values.
  - Fulwood, Ophelia, 1975 December 17; 344070 (Box 17, Reel 61a, Box 18, Reel 61b)
    Ophelia Fullwood was born in Morganton, North Carolina. She migrated north in 1941 and worked in Dover, Delaware and New York, New York. She worked in an ammunition factory and as a maid in private homes and hotels. She was employed as a maid at the time of the interview. She was a member of the Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union Local 6.
    This interview was conducted in the Bronx, New York by Sasha Silverstein on December 7, 1975. Main topics include Ophelia Fulwood's life in North Carolina, her migration north, her work as a maid, and her union activities. Fullwood recalls her early years in North Carolina including being raised by her mother's cousin; giving water to the workers on her grandfather's farm during the harvest season; leaving school in eighth grade to work as a maid; and learning about sex. Some of her first impressions of New York, New York include being shocked by the segregation in the US; not having warm clothes; and being afraid to be alone in New York City. She discusses her work as a maid, including her work schedule; the fact that she quit her job when her employers had marital problems; and that employment opportunities often came by word of mouth. When discussing her feelings on being a maid, Fulwood mentioned preferring day labor over sleep-in positions; that she loved being able to control her own schedule at the time of the interview; and that she was firm during the hiring process about what type of work she would do and how much she should be paid for it.
    African American women household employees |v Interviews.; Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union. Local 6 (Hotel, Restaurant and Club Employees Union) (New York, N.Y.)
  - Galinas, Mary MacCarthy, 1973 April 16; 593153 (Box 83, Reel 808a - 808b, Box 1, Folder 26)
    Mary MacCarthy Galinas was born on a farm in the late 1890s in County Kerry, Ireland and was the eldest of six children. She lived in Dublin, Ireland and London, England before immigrating to the United States in 1926, where she lived in Boston, Massachusetts and New York, New York. She worked as a waitress and married a French Canadian cook, with whom she had one daughter.
    This interview was recorded on April 16, 1973 at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York. The interviewer is likely Mary B. Alexander. The interview covers Mary MacCarthy Galinas' early life in Ireland and Great Britain, her immigration to the United States (US), her working life, and her family. Galinas recounts leaving her home in County Kerry, Ireland to care for her uncle's family in Dublin; moving to London, England to live with her sister; and remembering London as a place where British, Irish, and Scots all lived together harmoniously. She recounts her pride in being able to save a great deal of money before immigrating to the US. Topics regarding her life in Boston, Massachusetts include meeting her husband in one of the restaurants where she worked; continuing to work after her marriage and the birth of her daughter; and being unable to continue to save money after her marriage and the theft of her savings. Her discussion of New York, New York includes her decision to move there in the 1940s to gain better education opportunities for her daughter.
  - Gavin, Jimmy, 1974 May; 344071 (Box 101, Cd ref62, Box 18, Reel 62a - 62d, Box 19, Reel 62e - 62g)
    Jimmy Gavin was born in 1901 in Ballyvary, County Mayo, Ireland. He was one of eight children. His father was a building contractor, and his mother was a teacher until her marriage. Gavin attended an English national school in Ireland. He was a member of Irish Republican Army (IRA) and fought in both the Irish War of Independence and the Irish Civil War. He immigrated to the United States (US) during the mid-1920s. Gavin worked as a boatswain for the United States Coast Guard as well as for various commercial vessels. He was a member of the International Seamen's Union of America (ISU), a representative for the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), and an organizer for both of the aforementioned organizations.
    This interview was conducted by David Rosenberg and Mark Hirsch on two different dates in May 1974. The first interview was conducted by Rosenberg and Hirsch at an unknown location. A man identified as John also contributes to the interview. The second interview was conducted by Rosenberg at Jimmy Gavin's home in Brooklyn, New York. The volume of the recording fluctuates throughout the interview. This interview covers Gavin's childhood in Ireland; his involvement in the Irish War of Independence and the Irish Civil War; his immigration to the United States (US); and his work as a boatswain and an organizer for both the International Seamen's Union of America (ISU) and the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO). Gavin begins by explaining that he does not believe that the working class knows its own history, providing a timeline of events that he considers important to the development of the working class. He describes his childhood in Ireland, recalling his attendance at an English national school; his love of the Gaelic language and Irish history and literature; fishing and hunting trips; and the contrast between his father, who was a Marxist and anti-religion, and his mother, a devout Catholic. He describes joining the Irish Republican Army (IRA); leaving home at his father's behest in order to protect his family; not having a permanent home; learning how to use a gun; switching sides various times over the course of both the the Irish War of Independence and the Irish Civil War; and returning briefly to his home after he was declared dead.
    Gavin recounts traveling through England and deciding to immigrate to the US because the English police knew him to be a member of the IRA. He recalls writing to an aunt in the US who sent him the money to immigrate. He explains that he initially settled in Chicago, Illinois, where he worked transferring freight from boats. He describes his time working for the United States Coast Guard; the development of the ISU; his move to New York, New York; his contribution to organizing the Seamen's Unemployment Council in 1932; and various strikes for better conditions, particularly in terms of food quality and working hours. Other topics include his opinions on politicians and journalists; his political views; his work dissuading strikebreakers from occupying positions that union workers had vacated while on strike; and his trips across the US to organize labor unions.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States; and Unionization.
    Related Materials
    New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection, OH.001--Jimi Gavin.
    Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Labor and Radicalism Photograph Collection, PHOTOS.001--Gavin, D. J. ("Jimi").
    Marine Workers Historical Collection, TAM.125--Gavin, James (Jimmy): Memoirs and Poetry (unpublished).
    Ireland |x History |y Civil War, 1922-1923.; Ireland -- History -- War of Independence, 1919-1921
  - Geiss, Amelia, 1974 April 19; 344072 (Box 19, Reel 63a - 63b)
    Amelia Geiss was born in Hanover, Germany in 1909. She immigrated to the United States in 1929. She settled in New York, New York, where she met and married her husband. She worked mainly in restaurants and volunteered at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan after her retirement.
    This interview was conducted on April 19, 1974 by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York. The majority of this interview, covering the first 25 years of Amelia Geiss' life, was not recorded. Topics covered include Geiss' relationship with her husband; her experiences during the Great Depression; racial and ethnic tensions in her community in New York, New York; and her work at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center. Geiss spends the majority of the interview discussing her relationship with her husband, Bill, including how he was separated from his first wife when they first began their relationship; the fact that his estranged wife stalked Geiss; and the fact that she moved multiple times to escape this harassment. She discusses her husband's work as an electrician at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. She recalls that they survived the Great Depression due to the fact that they both were able to work. She discusses the community she lived in at the time of the interview, including how ethnic discrimination had gotten worse over time, and that the community had more problems at the time of the interview because it was no longer predominantly German. She discusses her volunteer work at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center, including the fact that she joined so that she and her husband would not fight after they retired; her fundraising efforts; both she and her husband being recognized by New York City for their work at the Center; and her participation on the Board of Directors.
  - Geller, Bessie, 1974 April 12 and 22; 344073 (Box 20, Reel 64a - 64d, Box 1, Folder 108)
    Bessie Geller was born in a small town in the Kiev region in Russia in the late 1890s. She was one of five children. Her father ran an unspecified business. Her mother helped Geller secretly hire a tutor for lessons in Russian literature, language, history, and geography. She was apprenticed in an unspecified trade in Russia and worked in an unspecified industry in the United States (US). She immigrated to the US with her sister and a friend in 1912, and the rest of her family immigrated the following year. She initially stayed with an uncle in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and later lived in both Chicago, Illinois and New York, New York. She attended an unspecified preparatory school in order to learn English. She married and had three daughters. Geller was an active Socialist and Anarchist and attended lectures, clubs, and meetings in order to learn more about radical political ideologies.